Guide to the Donald Chase Downes Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Donald Chase Downes Papers
1909-1979
1945-1979
MS 1453
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
3.75
(8 boxes)
The papers consist of correspondence, topical files, personal papers, and manuscripts which document the life of Donald Chase Downes during the early war years and after World War II. The papers highlight Downes's literary work and his research on the case of German General Anton Dostler. Also included in the papers is a copy of Peter Tompkins's journal of his life as a spy in Rome between 1942 and 1944.
Downes, Donald, 1903-
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Polly W. Downes, 1986; and Robin W. Winks, 1995.
Scope and Contents
The Donald Chase Downes Papers consist of correspondence, research and other topical files, personal papers, and writings which date primarily from Downes's life after he left the OSS. The files contain no more than scattered references to Downes's espionage work during World War II. The papers, which had been loaned to Robin Winks for his research in writing Cloak & Gown by Downes's sister-in-law Polly W. Downes, were received by the Manuscripts and Archives Department as the gift of Mrs. Downes in 1986.
The files are arranged in alphabetical order by record type. The files of correspondence in box 1 include many exchanges concerning Downes's research on Anton Dostler and the history of the doomed Ginny Mission. The correspondence also includes letters concerning Downes's efforts to return to Italy in 1955 and to his work in Beirut. Folder 12 which contains copies of some of Downes's outgoing letters at this time also includes his "promemoria" account of this effort. Boxes 2 and 3 include Downes's research material on military justice and war crimes. There is extensive documentation in these files on the Dostler case including the trial transcript and contemporary press coverage of the trial. Box 3 also contains a typescript copy of Peter Tompkins's journal from 1942 through 1944 and the manuscript for Tompkins's A Spy in Rome with Downes's editorial comments. The files also include the photographs which Tompkins intended to publish as illustrations in the book but which the publisher apparently decided not to use.* Manuscripts for Downes's books and unpublished writings fill boxes 4 and 5.
*Anyone wishing to quote from Tompkins's journal must first secure the permission of its author.
Biographical / Historical
Donald Chase Downes was born on September 30, 1903 in Catonsville, Maryland, the son of Joseph Lodowick and Effie Chase Downes. He attended Kent School, Phillips Exeter, and Yale College. He left Yale with the class of 1926 for teaching positions in Great Barrington, Massachusetts and at Cheshire Academy. He returned to Yale in 1930 and again in 1934-1935. After completing his course work, he received his B.A. from Yale in June 1935 and accepted a teaching position at a school on Cape Cod, where he lived for the next five years.
When in April 1940 Downes learned that the school was closing he decided to pursue a career in military intelligence. Downes received a reserve commission from the Office of Naval Intelligence (ONI) and secured a position as a teacher of English at Robert College in Turkey as cover for his espionage work. From October 1940 to March 1941 he worked for British intelligence in the Balkans, until he was ordered to return to the United States by ONI. He was then employed by the Free World Association from which position he spied on American isolationist groups for British intelligence. After the Japanese attack on Pearl Harbor Downes joined the American OSS, first operating in Washington, D.C. and, beginning in 1943, in North Africa and then Italy and Cairo. Downes's espionage work is detailed in Robin Winks's book, Cloak & Gown. Downes returned to Washington in August 1944, his intelligence career all but ended, but returned to Italy in February 1945 as a correspondent for a news agency. Downes remained in Europe at the end of the war, traveling and writing. In 1953 Downes published his wartime memoirs, The Scarlet Thread, and the following year collaborated on a cookbook, With Gusto and Relish. In September 1955 he was permitted to return to Italy where he continued his writing and achieved public recognition as an author for his spy thriller Orders to Kill, A Red Rose for Maria, and The Easter Dinner. In 1961 he assisted his friend Peter Tompkins in revising his wartime journal for publication as A Spy in Rome. Between 1969 and 1975 Downes researched questions of military justice and the prosecution of war criminals. He studied the case of German General Anton Dostler in depth, though he never published the results of his inquiry.
Downes moved to London in 1975 and returned to California in 1980. He died on March 26, 1983.
Conditions Governing Access
Due to the physical nature of the material, box 3 of Accession 1996-M-071 must be used under staff supervision..
Espionage; Intelligence service -- United States; Spies; War crimes; World War, 1939-1945 -- Italy; Manuscripts (for publication); Photoprints; Authors; Dostler, Anton, 1891-1945; Downes, Donald, 1903-; Tompkins, Peter
- Inventory
  - Correspondence
    - B - F, 1944-1969 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - G - N, 1955-1979 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - P - U, 1961-1979 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - W, 1969-1977 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Andress, William, Jr., 1969 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Bruce, David, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Emory, Kent, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Materazzi, Albert R., 1970 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - O'Brien, Philip J., Jr., 1969-1970, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Ullman, Robert, 1955, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
      General
      See also: box 1, folder 12
    - Unidentified, 1954-1978, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Letterbook with "promemoria,", 1955 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Diaries, 1959, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Financial and legal records, 1971, 1975-1976 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Medical records, 1964-1978 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Memorabilia, 1921-1968 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Notes, 1969, undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Printed material, 1965-1968, undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Topical files
    - Dostler, Anton
      - Downes's notes, 1969, undated (Box 2, Folder 19)
      - Trial transcript, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 20-22)
      - Trial documents, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 23)
      - Stars and Stripes -coverage of trial, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Italian resistance, undated (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Italy: maps and other background information, [1942, 1945] (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Kesselring, Albert, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Military justice, 1907-1965, undated (Box 2, Folder 28-32)
    - Tompkins, Peter: journal, 1942-1944 (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - Tompkins, Peter: "A Spy in Rome,", [ca. 1961] (Box 3, Folder 34-35)
    - Tompkins, Peter: "A Spy in Rome" - photographs, [ca. 1942-1944] (Box 3, Folder 36-39)
    - U.S. Department of Justice: registration statement, 1950-1961 (Box 3, Folder 40)
    - War crimes, 1945-1950, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Writings
    - "Amalfi I"-notebook, 1947 (Box 4, Folder 42)
    - "Beppo,", undated (Box 4, Folder 43)
    - "The Big Game Hunt,", undated (Box 4, Folder 44)
    - "Caldrons Bubble,", undated (Box 4, Folder 45)
    - "The Certificate of Naturalization" ("Miguel"), undated (Box 4, Folder 46)
    - "The Easter Dinner,", undated (Box 4, Folder 47-49)
    - "The Font of Type,", undated (Box 4, Folder 50)
    - "Hotel Marshal Plan/The Mayor of Priapino,", undated (Box 4, Folder 51)
    - "In Marble,", undated (Box 4, Folder 52)
    - "Justice and Liberty,", undated (Box 4, Folder 53)
    - "The Keywriting Expert,", undated (Box 4, Folder 54)
    - "The Ladies,", undated (Box 4, Folder 55)
    - "Ludi von Krazov,", undated (Box 4, Folder 56)
    - "Maria and Marcel,", undated (Box 4, Folder 57)
    - "Mishoui at Tarhit,", undated (Box 4, Folder 58)
    - "Mission to Budapest,", undated (Box 4, Folder 59)
    - "Orders to Kill,", undated (Box 4, Folder 60)
    - "Orders to Kill": filmscript, 1957 (Box 5, Folder 61)
    - "Pino,", undated (Box 5, Folder 62)
    - "The Port Lyauty Pilot's Story,", undated (Box 5, Folder 63)
    - "Queen Victoria's Conquest,", undated (Box 5, Folder 64)
    - "A Roman Tragedy,", undated (Box 5, Folder 65)
    - "The Scarlet Thread,", undated (Box 5, Folder 66)
    - "Signora Grossi Goes to Market,", undated (Box 5, Folder 67)
    - "With Gusto and Relish,", 1953-1954, undated (Box 5, Folder 68-72)
    - Notebooks, undated (Box 5, Folder 73-74)
    - Fragments and unidentified, undated (Box 5, Folder 75-77)
- Additional Material, Accession 1996-M-071
  Scope and Contents
  This addition to the Donald C. Downes Papers is arranged alphabetically by category to parallel the original arrangement of the papers. Materials are similar in type, with the exception of photographic materials in this addition, which have been located at the end of the collection.
  - Correspondence [incoming/outgoing and third party letters pertaining to D. Downes]
    - A - I, 1939-1943, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - K - M, 1939-1942 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - N - W, 1940-1942, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Allen, R. [Allen, W. Rowland?], 1942, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Lambert, Mrs. Lloyd, 1941-1942, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Roosevelt, Franklin Delano, 1941 November (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Stone, Grace, 1941-1942, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Ullman, Robert, 1940-1942, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Unidentified, 1939-1942, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Memorabilia, 1940-1942, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Notes, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Notes, fragments, miscellaneous, 1941, undated (Box 1, Folder 12-13)
  - Printed material, 1935-1942, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Subject files
    - Aliens, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - America First Committee, 1941-1942, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - American history [teaching notes], undated (Box 1, Folder 17-18)
    - Borgese, G. A. [typescript for article, "A.E.F. to Siberia,", 1942 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Chaillaux, Homer
    - Ingalls, Laura, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - International Free World Association, 1941-1942, undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
      See also: box 1, folder 8
    - Legal/personal [power of attorney, naval appointment], 1940, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - National Small Business Men's Association [Illinois Division], 1941 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Robert College (Istanbul, Turkey), 1929-1941 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - South Africa, undated (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Writings
    - "The Boy Who Cried Wolf,", undated (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - "Letter from a Pacifist,", 1941 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - "Mediterranean Front" [book review], undated (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - "Syria,", undated (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - "Why Help the Censors?,", undated (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Untitled,", undated (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Photographs/filmstrips
    - Individuals, groups of people, 1941, undated (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Cruise [possibly Pacific, Southeast Asia], undated (Box 2, Folder 33-34)
    - United States, undated (Box 2, Folder 35-36)
    - Scenic views, rural scenes, Damon House, 1941, undated (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Virginia [filmstrip], undated (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - United States, Pacific cruise, [ten rolled filmstrips, mostly unidentified], undated (Box 3)
      Conditions Governing Access
      Due to the physical nature of the material, rolled filmstrips must be used under staff supervision.